Hello and welcome to Week 4 of our Image and Video Processing class.
大家好 欢迎来到图像和视频处理第四周的课程
For the last few weeks, we have been very busy learning a lot of new concepts in
由于最近的几周我们已经学了很多的
image and video processing. This week, the materials are going to be
有关图像与视频处理的新概念 这周的内容会少一点
a bit short. I think we all deserve a shorter week
在学了如此之多新内容后
about after learning so much new material.
我觉得我们应当有一周稍微短一点
But also, the main reason this week is going to be a bit short in material is
但这周内容会短一点的主要原因是
because we're going to come back to some important examples of image restoration
当我们在图像处理课程中讨论更高级的内容时
later when we talk about more advanced topics in the class of image processing.
我们将再次回到一些重要的有关图像复原的实例上
But we still need to learn the basics of image restoration.
但我们仍需要学习图像复原的基础
And we need to understand what is image restoration.
并理解什么是图像复原
So, let's just go straight into that. But before that, just for a second,
我们直接进入主题吧 但在此之前
what background do you need for the topic of this week?
对于这周的主题 你需要了解哪些背景知识呢？
If you have knowledge about signal processing, and Fourier analysis,
如果你有信号处理与傅里叶分析的知识基础的话
there are some parts of the week that you might benefit a bit more.
在这周的某些部分中你会比较轻松
But since it happened in the previous weeks,
但鉴于在之前的几周也曾发生过
the material is going to be very self-contained so you should be able to
内容会比较独立 这样你应该能
understand the basic concepts with very limited background,
只要有很少的背景知识就能听懂基本概念
just some background in Linear Algebra mostly.
主要需要一些线性代数的背景知识
but again, Fourier analysis will be very helpful if you know it.
但是如果你知道傅里叶分析的话会更加有利
In particular, for the topic of Weiner filtering that we are going to explain
尤其是在 维纳滤波这一部分
in, in a few hours or actually in a few minutes.
一会儿我们会讲解到那里
So, let's just explain, what is image restoration?
那么 什么是图像复原呢？
So, in image restoration in contrast with image enhancement, we are going to try to
在图像复原中 与图像增强相对 我们将试着复原图像
restore the image. We are going to have a model for the
这有个图像的退化模型
degradation and that's what we see here. This is a degradation model.
就是我们在这里看见的 这就是退化模型
Basically, we start with an image. The image goes through some degradation
我们从一幅图像开始 图像经过退化后
which is represented by this filter H. Examples of degradation, and we're going
退化即由滤波器 H表示 在后面我们会详细地介绍
to discuss them in detail later on are, for example, blurring,
有关退化的实例 比如说模糊
defocus. When we take a picture that's out of focus, that's basically a
散焦 当我们拍了一张没有对焦的相片时
degradation. Another example is what's called motion
这就是一种退化 另外一个例子被称作运动模糊
blur. When we take pictures of something that
当我们拍运动得非常快的物体时
goes very fast, we actually see that as kind of blurry in our picture and that's
在相片中会看到一些模糊的地方
basically another type of degradation. After the image has gone through
这就是另外一种退化 在图像经过退化后
degradation, there is noise added to it. For example, the sensors in cameras have
还会有噪声的加入 例如相机中的传感器会产生噪声
noise, the sensors in magnetic resonance have noise.
处于磁共振中的传感器会产生噪声
So, there is noise added to it and this is what we actually observe, g.
于是就有噪声叠加进图像 这就是我们所观察到的 g
Now, from g, we need to go back to f as close as possible as the original f, and
现在从 g 我们需要回到 f 并尽可能地和原来的 f 保持一致
that's why this is called restoration. We're going to try to invert this
这就是为什么它被称为复原 我们将要试着逆转退化与噪声
degradation and noise, in order to be able to produce an image which is as
从而能够得到与之前尽可能贴近的图像
close as possible as the original image. So, this restored image, we want it to be
这个复原的图像 我们想让它与原来的图像尽可能一致
as close as possible to the original image. That's a goal of restoration.
这就是图像复原的目的
We didn't have that task in image enhancement, we just wanted it to look
在图像增强中我们并没有这样的目标 我们仅仅是
better, to look sharper, to benefit, let's say, our visual perception of the
想让它看上去更清楚 更锐化 这样有利于我们视觉上接收
image. The goal now is to actually restore the
而现在的目的就是复原这个图片
image. It's kind of a different goal, they're related, but it's kind of a
这是不同的目标 虽然它们间有一定关联
different goal, okay? And some of the things that we saw
但仍然是不同的 明白了吗？ 我们之前几周中
the previous week are actually very useful for image restoration as well, for
所了解的一些知识 实际上对图像复原也是很有用的
example, non-local means. You can show that under certain
例如非局部均值 你能看出它在某些特定情形下
conditions, restores the image. So, what's the model that we have here?
将图像复原了 那我们现在的模型是怎样呢？
How was g produced? g,
g 是如何产生的呢？
basically is a result of f going through the degradation.
它是f 经过退化的结果
So, we have f (x,y) convolution with H (x,y). That's a degredation model and
于是我们有 f ( x, y ) 与 H ( x, y )卷积 这就是退化模型
normally, it's assumed that is a linear operation.
通常这被视作一个线性的操作
So, it's a convolution. And we add to it the noise.
这是卷积 我们将其与噪声叠加
And most of the image and video processing literature leads with what's
大多数图像视频处理过程主要是有加性噪声
called additive noise. The noise is added to the image.
这种噪声加在了图像上
That's not what happens in all real cameras in all real acquisition devices,
并不是所有真正的相机或采集设备都会这样工作
for example. There is also multiplicative noise.
例如 还有乘性噪声
Very often, were basically all these, basically the degradation gets multiplied
通常来说 是指退化结果与一些噪音相乘
by some noise. There are other types of noise that
还有其它类型的噪音
happens, but these are some, two of the most common.
但这两种是最常见的
The most common of all is additive. Some literature, but much more limited,
最常见的是加性噪音 除此之外还存在比较有限的乘性噪音
addresses multiplicative noise. One of the effects of multiplicative
乘性噪音的一种效果是
noise is that the amount of noise depends on the signal itself.
噪音的量是由信号自身决定的
So, if the pixel value is three, we're multiplying three, but if the pixel value
如果像素值是三 我们就乘上三
is ten, we're multiplying ten, and then the amount of noise much, might be much
如果像素值是十 就乘上十 那么噪音的量可能会变得非常大
larger. And with additive noise, that doesn't
对于加性噪音就不会这样
happen. So, it's basically kind of
所以它去噪音的过程是
image-independent denoise. Now, there is a way to transform
与图像独立的 现在 有种方法
multiplicative noise into additive noise so we can enjoy all of the literature in
能将乘性噪音转化为加性噪音 于是我们能处理
additive noise and also work kind of with a small trick applied also to
所有含有加性噪音的图像 也可以处理经过一个小操作后的
multiplicative noise. And I wonder if you know what trick can
含乘性噪音的图像 我想你们是否知道我们使用的是什么技巧
we use to do that. Maybe think for a second before I give
在我告诉你们答案前可以想想看
you the answer. So, the question is very simple.
这个问题很简单
Think for yourself if you know what to do with multiplicative noise so you
先自己想想你们是否知道如何处理乘性噪音
transform it to additive noise. And let's think and I'll give you the
能将它转化为加性噪音 我们一起想想
answer very soon, okay?
我马上就会告诉你们答案 怎样？
You just spend some time thinking. Maybe you go to the answer very fast.
你就花点时间思考下 可能很快就有答案了
Maybe you go to the answer after a while or maybe you are waiting for me to give
或者你过会儿就想到 也可能你一直等着我告诉你答案
you the answer. And the idea is very simple.
这个思路很简单
If you have multiplicative noise instead of additive noise,
如果是乘性噪音而不是加性噪音的话
let me erase here, so I have everything to write down.
我先擦去这个 就有很多空间能写东西了
So, if you are multiplying two numbers, a times b, I can take the logarithmic of
那么 如果你将两个数相乘 a乘以b 我能对其取对数
those, of the product of those two numbers.
即对二者的积取对数
And that's equal to the logarithmic of a plus the log of b. So, I have trans, if b
那就等于a的对数加上b的对数 于是我得到了这个转换
was my noise, I basically transform it into additive noise.
假如b是我的噪音 这样就将其转化为加性噪音了
So, instead of working with the image, I'm going to work with the logarithmic
我们对图像的对数形式进行处理
version of the image and I'm going to work with the logarithmic component of
而不是直接对图像进行操作 于是我将对噪音的对数进行处理
the noise. So basically, you give me the degradation
当你给我退化的结果 g 图像
g, I take the log of g, and I treat everything that is now from
我取g的 log 并将其从此时起视作加性噪音
now on as it was additive noise. When I finish recovering it, I basically
当我完成复原之后
have to invert this operation. And that's an exponential function.
我需要进行这个的逆操作 也就是要用到指数函数
So, that's one of the reasons that a lot of the literature has basically
这也就是为什么很多的文献都致力于
concentrated on additive noise because of this trick.
处理加性噪音了 就是因为存在这个办法
Now, this trick has its own problems in particular because if you don't really
现在这个方法也有它自身的问题 尤其是
remove all the noise, the exponent can make it much, much larger.
若你没有去除所有的噪音 指数能将其放大很多很多
But it's an important trick that basically makes our additive noise,
但是它也是一个形成加性噪音的重要方法
restoration techniques also applicable to multiplicative noise with some caveats
复原技术也能应用于乘性噪音
and some limitations. So, having now a concept of what is image
只是有些注意事项与限制 现在 我们对图像复原有了一个基本概念
restoration, let's just talk in the next theory about
让我们探讨下一个有关噪音的理论吧
noise. What type of noise can we have in an
在一幅图像中我们会有何种噪音呢？
image? Where do they come from?
它们又来自何处？
So, see you in the next video to deal with that topic.
下个视频我们再讨论这个问题
Thank you.
谢谢大家